Finding Aid for James B. Angell Papers
Bentley Historical Library
- Subject Files and Personal Papers, 1845-1908; 3.4 linear feet, 1 oversize folder
  - Diaries
    - Volume 1, 1880-1881 (Box 13)
      (546)
    - Volume 2, 1880-1881 (Box 13)
      (547)
    - Typescript, 1880-1881 (Box 13)
  - Scrapbook of clippings from the Providence Journal, 1854-1859 (Box 13)
    (548)
  - Record book, 1872 (Box 13)
    (549)
  - Class register, 1908 (Box 13)
    (550)
  - Miscellaneous, 5 folders (Box 13)
  - Diplomas (James B. Angell and Sarah Swoope Caswell Angell) (Folder 1)
  - Clippings regarding James Burrill Angell's (JBA's) resignation (Box 13)
  - Clippings regarding JBA's Quarter Centennial celebration (Box 13)
  - Clippings regarding hazing, 1874 (Box 13)
  - Newspaper notices of JBA's The Reminiscences of James B. Angell, 1912 (Box 13)
  - Reports of Faculty Activities, 1875/76-1876/77 (Box 13)
  - Frieze (Henry S. and Anna) estate, 1891 (Box 13)
    (JBA was administrator)
  - Geology, Department of
    - Report from Eugene Hilliard, 1873 (Box 13)
    - Report from Alexander Winchell, 1889 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, programs and printed matter (Box 13)
  - Mr. Angell's Chinese Cards (Box 13)
- Photographs, 1 linear foot, 1 oversize boxes
  The Photographs series includes numerous formal photographic portraits of Angell as well shots of him working at his office and around campus. The series also contains a number of photographs of Angell's family members, such as his daughter, Lois Angell McLaughlin, father-in-law, Alexis Caswell, and wife, Sarah Caswell Angell.
  - Angell, Sarah Caswell (and members of Browning Club) (Box 14)
    (see also oversize in box 15)
  - Angell Family (Box 14)
  - Funeral (Box 14)
  - Exterior shots of Angell (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous (JBA and Harry Burns Hutchins) (Box 14)
  - Office Shots (Box 14)
  - Portraits, early (Box 14)
    (also oversize in box 15)
  - Portraits, late (Box 14)
  - Portraits, middle (Box 14)
  - Portraits, sculptured and paintings (photos) (Box 14)
  - Portraits, Signed (and Signature) (Box 14)
  - Album of Chinese prints (Box 14)
  - Album (Box 14)
  - Oversize photographs, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Oversize maps from Japan, 1 folder (Box 15)
Related Material
The Asia Library of the University of Michigan has obtained microfilm copies of Angell's correspondence written while serving in China. The originals of the microfilm are located in the National Archives in Washington D.C.
The Bentley also holds material from Angell's family including the Sarah Caswell Angell papers, the Lois T. McLaughlin papers, as well as the Alexis C. Angell papers.
Selective Index of Correspondents
Adams, Charles Kendall, 1835-1902.
1880-1882, Sept. 11, 1885, 1887-1890, Nov. 5, 1895, Dec. 23, 1895
Adams, Henry Carter, 1851-1921.
Apr. 6, 1882, March 20, 1884, July 15, 1885, March 25, 1886 (2 letters), Mar. 7, 1887, May 26, 1887, July 29, 1890, Dec. 3, 1890, Apr. 9, 1908, Apr. 18, 1908, June 15, 1908
Adams, Herbert Baxter
July 6, 1885
Arthur, Chester Alan, 1830-1886.
Apr. 12, 1882
Bagley, John Judson, 1832-1881.
Sept. 29, 1873, May 1, 1875, 1856, Jan. 1, 1877, Jan. 30, 1877, 1878, Feb. 20, 1879, Mar. 8, 1879, Mar. 26, 1880
Baldwin, Henry Porter, 1814-1892.
Dec. 7, 1872, June 30, 1875, Dec. 5, 1879, 1880
Barbour, Levi Lewis, 1840-1925.
Mar. 25, 1880, Mar. 1, 1895, Mar. 4, 1895, Mar. 2, 1897, July 24, 1899, July 28, 1899, Aug. 1, 1899, July 19, 1902, Jan. 23, 1903, 1904, 1905, June 25, 1906 (2 letters), July 14, 1906, Feb. 15, 1907, Mar. 11, 1907
Bates, Henry Moore, 1869-1949.
Nov. 7, 1899 (2 letters), July 10, 1903, Mar. 30, 1906, Dec, 12, 1907
Beard, Charles Austin, 1874-1948.
July 28, 1909
Blaine, James Gillespie, 1830-1893.
June 20, 1881; JBA to Blaine, May 21, June 18, July 2, 1881
Blair, Austin, 1818-1894.
Nov. 17, 1882, Feb. 12, 1883, Sept. 16, 1884, Oct. 20, 1884, Feb. 10, 1885
Bliss, Aaron Thomas, 1837-1906.
Mar. 18, 1901, Apr. 8, 1901, July 11, 1902, Dec. 10, 1902
Bryce, James Bryce, Viscount, 1838-1922.
Dec. 16, 1887
Burrows, Julius Caesar, 1837-1915.
Jan. 31, 1896, Feb. 29, 1896
Christiancy, Isaac Peckham, 1812-1890.
June 2, 1877, 1878
Cooley, Mortimer Elwyn, 1855-1915.
Jan. 21, 1904, Aug. 4, 1904, Nov. 19, 1904, Feb. 12, 1908, Apr. 20, 1908, Jan. 13, 1909, Jan. 31, 1909
Davis, Raymond Cazallis, 1836-1919.
1877, Apr. 1, 1881, Apr. 5, 1881, 1883, 1884
Demmon, Isaac Newton, 1842-1920.
July 2, 1872, June 20, 1876, Oct. 20, 1880
Dewey, John 1859-1952.
July 19, 1884, Apr. 19, 1889 (2 letters)
Dickinson, Donald McDonald, 1846-1917.
Sept. 4, 1885
D'Ooge, Martin Luther, 1839-1915.
July 5, 1877, July, 1879, June 17, 1880, Nov. 4, 1880, Dec. 22, 1880, May 7, 1881, Nov. 20, 1881, July 14, 1884
Eliot, Charles William, 1834-1925.
Oct. 2, 1871, Dec. 6, 1883, Nov. 14, 1884, Oct. 10, 1885, Apr. 22, 1886, Mar. 5, 1888, Geb. 6, 1890, Apr. 22, 1890, June 2, 1890, June 3, 1892, Mar. 1, 1893, Apr. 11, 1893, Nov. 18, 1893, Nov. 19, 1895, Oct. 9, 1895, Feb. 29, 1896, Nov. 23, 1896, Feb. 8, 1899, Nov. 19, 1899, Aug. 28, 1902, May 22, 1903
Fairlie, John Archibald, 1872-1947.
June 1, 1900, June 26, 1901, Apr. 2, 1908
Ferris, Woodbridge Nathan, 1853-1928.
Sept. 14, 1895, Sept. 19, 1895, Sept. 21, 1895, Apr. 20, 1896, June 1, 1896, May 12, 1899, July 4, 1899
Fletcher, Frank Ward, 1853-1922.
Mar. 3, 1897, Mar. 3, 1899, Nov. 23, 1904, Mar. 24, 1905, June 2, 1905, Jan. 25, 1906, Mar. 12, 1906, Jan. 28, 1907 (2 letters), 1908
Frieze, Henry Simmons, 1817-1899.
1869, Jan. 29, 1870, 1871, 1872, Aug. 12, 1874, July, 1844, Feb. 12, 1878, May 30, 1879, 1880, 1881, Feb. 2, 1882, Feb. 27, 1882, Apr. 5, 1882, July 14, 1883, July 19, 1883
Garfield, James Abram, 1831-1881.
Mar. 15, 1879
Grosvenor, Ebenezer Oliver, 1820-1910.
Mar. 5, 1880, Mar. 8, 1880, Feb. 28, 1881, July 14, 1882, 1883, Apr. 13, 1885
Hale, Edward Everett, 1822-1909.
June 8, 1880, July 19, 1885
Haven, Erastus Otis, 1820-1881.
Sept. 27, 1871, June 1, 1880
Hay, John, 1838-1905.
Aug. 2, 1873, May 18, 1874, Dec. 8, 1879, Apr. 13, 1880, Mar. 1, 1906
Hayes, Rutherford Birchard, 1822-1893.
Jan. 5, 1883
Hill, Arthur, 1847-1909.
Dec. 26, 1903, 1904, Oct. 21, 1905, Dec. 26, 1908, Apr. 5, 1908, Apr. 25, 1908
Hobbs, William Herbert, 1864-1953.
Aug. 30, 1903, Nov. 18, 1903, Aug. 7, 1906, Dec. 11, 1906
Hutchins, Harry Burns, 1847-1930.
Aug. 27, 1874, Aug. 30, 1884, Apr. 8, 1894, Sept. 26, 1984, May 3, 1894, July 23, 1895, Sept. 7, 1898
Jerome, David Howell, 1829-1896.
Nov. 17, 1882, Nov. 20, 1882
Jordan, Myra Beach, 1850-
July 1, 1902, Mar. 23, 1908, Apr. 7, 1909
Joy, James Frederick, 1810-1896.
Dec. 14, 1882, Dec. 15, 1882, Dec. 18, 1882, 1883-1885
Kelsey, Francis Willey, 1858-1927.
June 27, 1889 (2 letters), Mar. 23, 1893, Apr. 18, 1893
Kiefer, Hermann, 1825-1911.
July 27, 1889, Dec. 18, 1890, July 25, 1893, Jan. 5, 1900, June 24, 1902
Knappen, Loyal Edwin, 1854-193-.
1905, Oct. 1, 1906, Dec. 9, 1906, Dec. 28, 1906, Feb. 14, 1907, Mar. 23, 1907, Mar. 28, 1907, Dec. 30, 1908, Feb. 4, 1908, July 27, 1909, July 22, 1909
Low, Seth, 1850-1916.
Oct. 1, 1891, June 3, 1892, May 23, 1896, Dec. 3, 1900, Mar. 25, 1901, May 11, 1901, May 13, 1901
Luce, Cyrus Gray, 1824-1905.
Dec. 11, 1886, Dec. 18, 1886, Dec. 22, 1886, Nov. 26, 1888, Dec. 3, 1888, Jan. 19, 1889, Dec. 2, 1890, Dec. 27, 1890
McMillan, James, 1838-1902.
Dec. 16, 1882, May 8, 1883, June 14, 1883, Sept. 5, 1885, Sept. 8, 1885, Oct. 29, 1885, May 15, 1887, May 28, 1887, Jan. 15, 1889, Sept. 5, 1889, Dec. 20, 1889, Dec. 17, 1890, Dec. 27, 1890, Mar. 31, 1891, Jan. 19, 1899, Nov. 22, 1899
Morrill, Justin Smith, 1810-1898.
Oct. 18, 1859, Feb. 17, 1870, July 27, 1871.
Mosher, Eliza Maria, 1846-1928.
Oct. 30, 1895, Dec. 19, 1895, Jan. 11, 1896, Apr. 15, 1902, Sept. 30, 1902
Olney, Richard, 1835-1917.
1895, 1896
Palmer, Alice Freeman, 1855-1902.
June 3, 1896; letters dated Apr. 14, 1882, Feb. 25, 1884, May 13, 1891 located in Palmer collection.
Palmer, Thomas Witheroll, 1830-1913.
July 24, 1876, Nov. 9, 1878
Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946.
Feb. 8, 1909, Feb. 16, 1909, Mar. 5, 1909
Pingree, Hazen Smith, 1840-1901.
Mar. 8, 1899, Apr. 1899
Shurz, Carl, 1829-1906.
Nov. 1, 1871, Jan. 17, 1876, Feb. 28, 1877
Smith, William Alden, 1859-1902.
Nov. 4, 1885, Feb. 1, 1896
Spaulding, Oliver Lyman, 1833-1922.
June 2, 1892, June 16, 1892
Stearns, Frederick Kimball, 1831-1907.
Oct. 16, 1893, Apr. 25, 1894, Apr. 20, 1894, 1898, Aug. 14, 1899, July 1, 1900, June 28, 1901
Steere, Joseph Beale, 1842-1940.
Apr. 5, 1876, Sept. 5, 1876, July 5, 1877, July 24, 1877
Sullivan, Louis Henry, 1856-1924.
Dec. 15, 1905
Tappan, Henry Philip, 1805-1881.
Nov. 12, 1874, Oct. 14, 1875
Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1901.
July 16, 1871, Jan. 12, 1872, Jan. 23, 1872, 1873, 1874, Jan. 22, 1877, July 10, 1877, Feb. 12, 1878, May 30, 1879, Oct. 24, 1880, Mar. 5, 1881, May 25, 1881 (2 letters), Mar. 1, 1882, June 12, 1885, July 21, 1885, July 2, 1887
Warner, Fred Maltby, 1876-1923.
1905, 1908, Jan. 6, 1909, Feb. 24, 1909
Wenley, Robert Mark, 1871-1929.
Sept. 24, 1895, Oct. 22, 1895, 1896, Apr. 2, 1901, May 10, 1901, 1905, Jan. 13, 1906, Aug. 9, 1906
White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.
Sept. 13, 1869, Oct. 2, 1871, Aug. 25, 1873, Dec. 12, 1873, Mar. 27, 1874, May 30, 1874, Sept. 30, 1874, May 8, 1875, Apr. 8, 1879, Apr. 9, 1879, July 30, 1879, Jan. 3, 1868
Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924.
Nov. 7, 1887, Nov. 15, 1887
Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891.
Feb. 19, 1877, June 7, 1880, Feb.3, 1889